Guide to the M.T. Jones Lumber Co. records and business ledgers, 1880-1940 MS 629
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
M.T. Jones Lumber Co. records and business ledgers
1880-1940
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
M. T. Jones Lumber Company
MS 629
43.5 Linear Feet (65 boxes)
The M.T. Jones Lumber Co. Records & Business Ledgers, 1890-1920, consist of business records, correspondence, letterpress books, invoices, orders, shipping records, and ledgers for the daily operations and administration of the lumber company for Texas, Oklahoma, New Mexico, Arizona and Colorado.
Biographical / Historical
Martin Tilford Jones, brother of William Hasque Jones/father of Jesse H. Jones, was born in 1841 in Robertson County, Tennessee, and died June 22, 1898 in Houston, TX. He was the fifth of six siblings. He enlisted in the Union Army in 1861 and was mustered out in 1865. After the war he married Louisa Woolard (1849-1934) and had three children: Augusta (1867-1960), Wiliam Eli (1871-1937), and Adiliene Jeanette (1877- ). After farming in Illinois, he moved to Terrell, Texas in 1875 to open a small lumber yard. He moved to Houston in 1883 and two years later organized the M.T. Jones Lumber Company and began acquiring property and timber rights and built saw mills, mostly in east Texas. He built a hugely successful business with an estimated six-five lumber yards mainly in Texas, but also in New Mexico, Colorado, Arizona and Oklahoma. M.T.'s nephew, Jesse H. Jones worked for the Dallas lumberyard, and when M.T. died, Jesse Jones moved to Houston to manage his estate.
Scope and Contents
The M.T. Jones Lumber Co. Records & Business Ledgers, 1890-1920, consist of business records, correspondence, letterpress books, invoices, orders, shipping records, and ledgers for the daily operations and administration of the lumber company for Texas, Oklahoma, New Mexico, Arizona and Colorado.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open for use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated by Houston Endowment, Inc. in Oct. 2014.
Related Materials
See also "A Guide to the M.T. Jones Lumber Company Records, 1883-1914," Briscoe Center for American History, the University of Texas at Austin; and Jesse H. Jones Family & Personal Papers, MS 252, Woodson Research Center, Fondren Library, Rice University.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in three series, with various sub-series as necessary: Series I: Administrative; Series II: Operations ledgers; Series III: Lumberyard general accounting ledgers.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586. Boxes 23-24, 32-33, 35-36, 38, 40-49, 51-52, 54, 56-62, and 65 are unprocessed/unavailable.
Index Terms
Subjects
Business; Frontier life
Document Types
financial records; letters (correspondence)
Subjects (Persons)
Jones, Martin Tilford (M. T.)
- Series I: Adminstrative, 226517
  - Balance sheet, 1890-1892; 226545 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letterhead & correspondence, 1892-1908; 226554 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Notes receivable, 1896-1898; 226547 (Box 1)
    - 1896-98, 226555 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1898-1904, 226556 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1904-05, 226557 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1905-07, 226558 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Stockholder meeting minutes, 1906; 226551 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Legal: Weyland Wilson judgment, 1908; 226552 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Acquistion by Houston Endowment, Inc., 1984; 226553 (Box 1, Folder 9-11)
- Series II: Operations ledgers, 226559
  - General business accounting, 226560
    - 1885-86, 234611 (Box 2)
    - 1888-89, 226561 (Box 3)
    - 1889-91, 226562 (Box 4)
    - 1891-92, 226563 (Box 5)
    - 1892-94, 226564 (Box 6)
  - Accounts, 227206
    - 1881-82, 227217 (Box 7)
    - 1882-84, 227218 (Box 7)
    - 1888, 227207 (Box 8)
    - 1889 (also by lumberyard), 227208 (Box 9)
    - 1891, 227209 (Box 10)
    - 1891 (also by lumberyard), 227210 (Box 11)
    - 1892, 227246 (Box 11)
    - 1895-98 by lumberyard, 227211 (Box 12)
    - 1898, 227247 (Box 13)
    - 1898-1900, 227227 (Box 13)
    - 1905-06, 227250 (Box 14)
    - Index, 227251 (Box 14)
    - 1907-08, 227253 (Box 15)
    - 1908, 227254 (Box 15)
    - 1908, 227255 (Box 16)
    - 1915-16, 227256 (Box 17)
  - Cash, 227212
    - 1883, 227257 (Box 18)
    - 1890-91, 227258 (Box 18)
    - 1890-93, 227260 (Box 18)
    - 1890-93, 227262 (Box 18)
    - 1891-92, 227261 (Box 18)
    - 1893-98, 227269 (Box 19)
    - 1895-97, 227270 (Box 19)
  - Orders/invoices, 227314
    - 1882, 227315 (Box 20)
    - 1889-90, 227316 (Box 20)
    - 1890, 227317 (Box 20)
    - 1891-92, 229940 (Box 21)
    - 1892-93, 229941 (Box 22)
    - 1894, 227318 (Box 22)
    - 1895-96, 227319 (Box 23)
    - 1896, 227324 (Box 23)
    - 1897 letterpress, 227320 (Box 24-25)
    - 1898 letterpress, 227327 (Box 26)
    - 1898-1904 letterpress, 227328 (Box 26)
    - 1899, 227329 (Box 27)
    - 1900, 249168 (Box 27)
    - 1900-01 letterpress, 229944 (Box 26)
    - 1901, 227330 (Box 28-29)
    - 1901-02, 227331 (Box 30)
    - 1902, 227332 (Box 31)
  - Shipments, 229948
    - 1890-91, 229950 (Box 32)
    - 1890-94, 238379 (Box 33)
    - 1891-92, 229952 (Box 33)
    - 1897, 229955 (Box 33)
- Series III: Lumberyard general accounting ledgers, 229957
  - Albany, TX, 230051
    - 1907-08, 230057 (Box 34)
  - Amarillo, TX, 230053
    - 1903-06, 230055 (Box 34)
    - 1904, 230060 (Box 34)
    - 1905, 230061 (Box 34)
  - Bokchito, OK, 230063
    - 1903-05, 230065 (Box 34)
    - 1905-06, 230067 (Box 35)
    - 1907-08, 230069 (Box 35)
  - Brownwood, TX, 230070
    - 1907-08, 230071 (Box 36)
    - 1908-09, 230073 (Box 37)
    - 1909-11, 230075 (Box 37)
  - Caddo, TX, 230077
    - 1903-07, 230079 (Box 36)
    - 1907-08, 230080 (Box 37)
    - 1908-10, 230081 (Box 37)
  - Cale, TX, 230084
    - 1903-06, 230085 (Box 37)
    - 1907-11, 230087 (Box 38)
  - Canyon, TX, 230088
    - 1902-04, 230090 (Box 39)
    - 1907, 230091 (Box 37)
    - 1909-10, 230092 (Box 37)
  - Carbon, TX, 230093
    - 1904-06, 230094 (Box 39)
    - 1906-09, 230096 (Box 39)
    - 1909-11, 230097 (Box 39)
  - Cisco, TX, 230100
    - 1903-06, 230101 (Box 40)
    - 1904-06, 230102 (Box 41)
    - 1907, 230104 (Box 42)
    - 1908-09, 230105 (Box 43-44)
  - Colorado, 230098
    - 1905-06, 230099 (Box 39)
  - Durant, OK, 230107
    - 1905-06, 230109 (Box 45)
    - 1908-11, 230110 (Box 46)
    - 1913-14, 230112 (Box 47)
    - 1919-20, 230113 (Box 48)
  - Friona, TX, 238384
    - 1907-10, 239312 (Box 49)
  - Ft. Sumner, NM, 230115
    - 1910-11, 230117 (Box 50)
  - Hereford, TX, 230118
    - 1902-04, 230120 (Box 50)
    - 1905-06, 230121 (Box 50)
    - 1907, 230123 (Box 50)
  - Houston, TX, 232225
    - Rockwell Bros. 1897, 232226 (Box 51)
    - Rockwell Bros. 1897-98, 232227 (Box 52)
  - Laredo, TX, 230127
    - 1891-94, 230128 (Box 50)
    - 1894-97, 232224 (Box 53)
    - 1896, 230130 (Box 50)
    - 1897, 230131 (Box 50)
  - Llano, TX, 230141
    - 1908-11, 230142 (Box 54)
  - Lueders, TX, 230143
    - 1907-08, 230145 (Box 55)
  - McAlester, OK, 230147
    - 1903-04, 230149 (Box 55)
    - 1905-07, 230150 (Box 56)
    - 1908-10, 230151 (Box 57)
    - 1910-11, 230152 (Box 58)
  - Midland, TX, 232184
    - 1902-05, 232185 (Box 59)
    - 1906-07, 232187 (Box 60)
    - 1908-11, 232188 (Box 61)
  - Mineral Wells, TX, 230154
    - 1905-06, 230156 (Box 55)
    - 1907, 230157 (Box 55)
  - Moran, TX, 230159
    - 1906-08, 230160 (Box 55)
  - Phoenix, AZ, 232217
    - 1890-98, 232218 (Box 64)
  - Plainview, TX, 230162
    - 1906-07, 230163 (Box 55)
    - 1908-09, 232190 (Box 63)
    - 1914-16, 232191 (Box 62)
  - Portales, NM, 232192
    - 1903-05, 232193 (Box 63)
    - 1906-07, 232194 (Box 63)
    - 1907-09, 232195 (Box 63)
  - Rising Star, TX, 232197
    - 1908-10, 232201 (Box 63)
  - Rising Sun, TX [?] OK [?], 239545
    - 1906-08, 239546 (Box 63)
  - South Texas, 232203
    - 1900 letterpress, 232204 (Box 63)
  - Sweetwater, TX, 232205
    - 1910, 232207 (Box 64)
  - Tulia, TX, 232208
    - 1906-07, 232209 (Box 64)
    - 1907-11, 232211 (Box 64)
    - 1908, 232210 (Box 64)
  - Umbarger, TX, 232212
    - 1909-11, 232213 (Box 64)
  - Yoakum, TX, 232214
    - 1904-05, 232215 (Box 65)
    - 1905-07, 232216 (Box 65)